export const quizzes = [
    {
      title: "Week 1",
      questions: [
        { question: "1. <b>'Enquiry into plants'</b> is a book written by", options: ["a. Theophrastus","b. Linnaeus","c. Malthus","d. Humboldt"], answer: "a. Theophrastus" },
        { question: "2. In the <b>Greek</b> word root of Ecology, <b>Oikos</b> refers to", options: ["a. household", "b. preservation", "c. environment", "d. study"], answer: "a. household" },
        { question: "3. In the <b>Greek</b> word root of Ecology, <b>logos</b> refers to", options: ["a. household", "b. preservation", "c. environment","d. study"], answer: "d. study" },
        { question: "4. <b>Ecology</b> is the <b>scientific study of interactions</b> among organisms and their ___. (Fill in the blanks)", options: ["a. habitat", "b. niche", "c. environment","d. population"], answer: "c. environment" },
        { question: "5. Who amongst these is considered the <b>father of Biogeography</b>?", options: ["a. Theophrastus", "b. Linnaeus", "c. Malthus","d. Humboldt"], answer: "d. Humboldt"},
        { question: "6. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>characteristic of fitness</b>?", options: ["a. Fitness is environment-specific.", "b. Fitness is species-specific.", "c. Higher reproductive rate means higher fitness.","d. Fitness should be measured across several generations."], answer: "c. Higher reproductive rate means higher fitness."},
        { question: "7. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>kind of selection</b>", options: ["a. directional", "b. stochastic", "c. disruptive","d. stabilising"], answer: "b. stochastic"},
        { question: "8. Ecology is the scientific study of ___ that <b>determine the distribution and abundance of organisms</b>. (Fill in the blanks)", options: ["a. statics", "b. interactions", "c. dynamics","d. habitat"], answer: "b. interactions"},
        { question: "9. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>characteristic of fitness</b>?", options: ["a. Fitness is environment-specific.", "b. Fitness is species-specific.", "c. Fitness works on traits such as size and speed.","d. Fitness should be measured across several generations."], answer: "c. Fitness works on traits such as size and speed."},
        { question: "10. Which of these is <b>not a step in natural selection</b>?", options: ["a. variation", "b. underpopulation", "c. struggle for existence","d. survival of the fittest"], answer: "b. underpopulation"}
        
      ]
    },

    {
        title: "Week 2",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. Hierarchy emerges almost inevitably through a <b>wide variety of evolutionary processes</b>, for the simple reason that hierarchical structures are ___ (Fill in the blank)", options: ["a. perfect","b. imperfect","c. stable","d. unstable"], answer: "c. stable" },
          { question: "2. The <b>mitochondrion</b> is a / an", options: ["a. Sub-cellular organelle", "b. Cell", "c. Tissue", "d. Organ"], answer: "a. Sub-cellular organelle" },
          { question: "3. The <b>laboratory approach</b> to Ecology uses", options: ["a. equations", "b. models", "c. observations","d. experiments"], answer: "d. experiments" },
          { question: "4. 'The <b>diversity</b> that exists <b>among different geographies</b>' is", options: ["a. alpha (α) biodiversity", "b. beta (β) biodiversity", "c. gamma (γ) biodiversity","d. delta (δ) biodiversity"], answer: "c. gamma (γ) biodiversity" },
          { question: "5. The <b>hierarchical system</b> was given by", options: ["a. Simon", "b. Watson", "c. Hutchinson","d. Humboldt"], answer: "a. Simon"},
          { question: "6. 'groups of actually or potentially <b>interbreeding</b> natural populations, which are <b>reproductively isolated</b> from other such groups' is a definition of", options: ["a. cells", "b. species", "c. ecosystems","d. biomes"], answer: "b. species"},
          { question: "7. 'The <b>diversity</b> that <b>exists within an ecosystem</b>' is", options: ["a. alpha (α) biodiversity","b. beta (β) biodiversity","c. gamma (γ) biodiversity","d. delta (δ) biodiversity"], answer: "a. alpha (α) biodiversity"},
          { question: "8. The <b>emergent principle</b> can be stated as", options: ["a. Whole = sum of parts","b. Whole < sum of parts","c. Whole > sum of parts","d. None of these"], answer: "c. Whole > sum of parts"},
          { question: "9. There is <b>more biodiversity</b> in areas with", options: ["a. less competition, less predation","b. less competition, more predation","c. more competition, more predation","d. more competition, less predation"], answer: "c. more competition, more predation"},
          { question: "10. For more <b>biodiversity</b>, the <b>level of disturbance</b> should be", options: ["a. less","b. intermediate","c. more","d. none of these"], answer: "b. intermediate"}
          
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 3",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. <b>Birds on giraffe</b> are an example of", options: ["a. colony","b. commensalism","c. protocooperation","d. allelopathy"], answer: "c. protocooperation" },
          { question: "2. <b>Egrets with buffaloes</b> are an example of", options: ["a. colony","b. commensalism","c. protocooperation","d. allelopathy"], answer: "b. commensalism" },
          { question: "3. The <b>scientific study of animal behaviour</b> is called", options: ["a. behaviourism","b. ecology","c. ethology","d. prey-predator dynamics"], answer: "c. ethology" },
          { question: "4. The <b>interaction</b> between <b>exotic shrubs and trees</b> through the <b>action of seed predators</b> is an example of", options: ["a. infraspecific competition","b. apparent competition","c. disguised competition","d. harmonious competition"], answer: "b. apparent competition" },
          { question: "5. <b>Harmonious interactions occur</b> where", options: ["a. at least one participant is benefited","b. at least one participant is unharmed","c. both participants are benefitted","d. both participants are unharmed"], answer: "d. both participants are unharmed"},
          { question: "6. <b>Hamilton's rule</b> can be stated as", options: ["a. rB < C","b. rB > C","c. rB = C","d. rB + C = 0"], answer: "b. rB > C"},
          { question: "7. <b>Trampling of grass</b> due to the movement of animals is an example of", options: ["a. mutualism","b. ammensalism","c. commensalism","d. protocooperation"], answer: "b. ammensalism"},
          { question: "8. I observe a <b>monkey take a tick out of another monkey's head</b> and eat it. In the social context, this behaviour would be called", options: ["a. tick hunting","b. auto grooming","c. allo grooming","d. foraging"], answer: "c. allo grooming"},
          { question: "9. <b>An inventory of behaviours</b> exhibited by an animal <b>during a behaviour exercise</b> is called", options: ["a. ecogram","b. ethogram","c. behaviourogram","d. animalogram"], answer: "b. ethogram"},
          { question: "10. <b>I observe a bird take a tick out of another bird's head</b> and eat it. In the social context, this behaviour would be called", options: ["a. tick hunting","b. auto grooming","c. allo grooming","d. foraging"], answer: "c. allo grooming"}
          
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 4",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. Consider the food chain: Grass → Grasshopper → Frog → Snake →Hawk. As we <b>move up the food chain</b>,", options: ["a. available energy decreases","b. available energy increases","c. available energy remains same","d. available energy is zero everywhere"], answer: "a. available energy decreases" },
          { question: "2. Consider the food chain: Grass → Grasshopper → Frog → Snake →Hawk. In this food chain,", options: ["a. hawk is producer","b. hawk is consumer and carnivore","c. hawk is consumer and herbivore","d. hawk is decomposer"], answer: "b. hawk is consumer and carnivore" },
          { question: "3. Trees → Birds → Parasites → Hyperparasites represents", options: ["a. upright pyramid of numbers","b. inverted pyramid of numbers","c. spindle pyramid of numbers","d. dumb-bell pyramid of numbers"], answer: "b. inverted pyramid of numbers" },
          { question: "4. Consider the food chain: Grass → Grasshopper → Frog → Snake →Hawk. In this food chain,", options: ["a. frog is producer","b. frog is consumer and carnivore","c. frog is consumer and herbivore","d. frog is decomposer"], answer: "b. frog is consumer and carnivore" },
          { question: "5. At the compensation point,", options: ["a. photosynthesis = respiration","b. photosynthesis < respiration","c. photosynthesis > respiration","d. photosynthesis = 0"], answer: "a. photosynthesis = respiration"},
          { question: "6. Tree → Frugivorous birds → Hawk represents", options: ["a. upright pyramid of numbers","b. inverted pyramid of numbers","c. spindle pyramid of numbers","d. dumb-bell pyramid of numbers"], answer: "c. spindle pyramid of numbers"},
          { question: "7. <b>Glacial lakes</b> are typical examples of", options: ["a. eutrophic lakes","b. hypereutrophic lakes","c. oligotrophic lakes","d. mesotrophic lakes"], answer: "c. oligotrophic lakes"},
          { question: "8. Consider the food chain: Grass → Grasshopper → Frog → Snake →Hawk. In this food chain,", options: ["a. more number of hawks than grasshoppers can be supported","b. more number of grasshoppers than hawks can be supported","c. equal number of hawks and grasshoppers can be supported","d. none of these"], answer: "b. more number of grasshoppers than hawks can be supported"},
          { question: "9. If we <b>all became vegetarians</b>, we'll be able to support our large populations. This can be explained through", options: ["a. 10% rule","b. 1% rule","c. trophic cascade","d. biodiversity"], answer: "a. 10% rule"},
          { question: "10. <b>Net primary productivity</b> is given by", options: ["a. APAR × LUE","b. APAR + LUE","c. APAR - LUE","d. APAR / LUE"], answer: "a. APAR × LUE"}
          
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 5",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. ___ is <b>how close</b> the <b>measured values are to the correct value.</b>", options: ["a. Accuracy","b. Precision","c. Bias","d. Variance"], answer: "a. Accuracy" },
          { question: "2. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>measure of absolute population density</b>?", options: ["a. total count","b. pelt count","c. capture-recapture method","d. removal method"], answer: "b. pelt count" },
          { question: "3. <b>The logistic growth equation</b>, when plotted, appears", options: ["a. I shaped","b. J shaped","c. S shaped","d. O shaped"], answer: "c. S shaped" },
          { question: "4. ___ employs a simple rule of selecting every kth unit starting with a number chosen at <b>random from 1 to k as the random start</b>.", options: ["a. Simple random sampling","b. Systematic sampling","c. Stratified sampling","d. Multistage sampling"], answer: "b. Systematic sampling"},
          { question: "5. <b>The juvenile mortality rate</b> is the annual number of deaths of juveniles per", options: ["a. 100 births","b. 1000 births","c. 100 live births","d. 1000 live births"], answer: "d. 1000 live births" },
          { question: "6. The <b>minimum replacement level fertility</b> for a population to grow should be <b>greater than</b>", options: ["a. 1","b. 2","c. 3","d. 4"], answer: "b. 2"},
          { question: "7. <b>Pan traps</b> are used for sampling", options: ["a. bees","b. butterflies","c. non-pollinator insects","d. pollinator insects"], answer: "d. pollinator insects"},
          { question: "8. Which of these is true?", options: ["a. Physiological longevity > Ecological longevity","b. Physiological longevity = Ecological longevity","c. Physiological longevity < Ecological longevity","d. a or b"], answer: "d. a or b"},
          { question: "9. A sampling procedure such that each possible combination of sampling units out of the population has the <b>same chance of being selected</b> is referred to as", options: ["a. Simple random sampling","b. Systematic sampling","c. Stratified sampling","d. Multistage sampling"], answer: "a. Simple random sampling"},
          { question: "10. <b>Cover board surveys</b> are typically used for sampling", options: ["a. herpetofauna","b. fishes","c. large mammals","d. carnivores"], answer: "a. herpetofauna"}
                  
        ]
      },
      
      {
        title: "Week 6",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. A <b>climax caused by wildfires</b> is an example of", options: ["a. climatic climax","b. edaphic climax","c. disclimax","d. catastrophic climax"], answer: "d. catastrophic climax" },
          { question: "2. When compared to generalist species, <b>specialist species</b> have", options: ["a. narrower niches","b. broader niches","c. same-size niches","d. none of these"], answer: "a. narrower niches" },
          { question: "3. Which of these <b>depicts</b> correctly the <b>lithosere primary succession</b>? R Cl F M H S W C", options: ["a. Rock → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Moss →Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax","b. Rock → Foliose lichen → Crustose lichen → Moss →Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax","c. Moss → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Rock →Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax","d. Rock → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Shrub →Herbaceous stage → Moss → Woodland → Climax"], answer: "a. Rock → Crustose lichen → Foliose lichen → Moss →Herbaceous stage → Shrub → Woodland → Climax" },
          { question: "4. <b>Importance value</b> can be <b>written as</b>", options: ["a. Relative density + Relative frequency X Relative dominance","b. Relative density X Relative frequency + Relative dominance","c. Relative density + Relative frequency + Relative dominance","d. Relative density X Relative frequency X Relative dominance"], answer: "c. Relative density + Relative frequency + Relative dominance" },
          { question: "5. <b>Lithosere</b> is an example of", options: ["a. hydrosere","b. xerosere","c. psammosere","d. halosere"], answer: "b. xerosere"},
          { question: "6. <b>Importance value</b> -- <b>varies from</b>", options: ["a. 0 to 10","b. 0 to 50","c. 0 to 100","d. 0 to 300"], answer: "d. 0 to 300"},
          { question: "7. A <b>species found</b> most frequently <b>in a particular community</b>, but <b>also present occasionally in others</b> is called", options: ["a. accidental species","b. indifferent species","c. selective species","d. exclusive species"], answer: "c. selective species"},
          { question: "8. The <b>climax near Tindni village</b> is being controlled by disturbance by cattle. This is an example of", options: ["a. climatic climax","b. edaphic climax","c. disclimax","d. catastrophic climax"], answer: "c. disclimax"},
          { question: "9. Which of these is correct?", options: ["a. Fundamental niche > Realised niche","b. Fundamental niche = Realised niche","c. Fundamental niche < Realised niche","d. a or b"], answer: "d. a or b"},
          { question: "10. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>characteristic of pioneer species</b>", options: ["a. ability to grow on bare rocks","b. ability to tolerate extreme temperatures","c. large size","d. short life span"], answer: "c. large size"}
          
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 7",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. I tried <b>growing vegetables under my teak plantation</b>, but the vegetable plants <b>died out</b>. I should be concerned about", options: ["a. autophagy","b. allelophagy","c. autopathy","d. allelopathy"], answer: "d. allelopathy" },
          { question: "2. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>physical factor of habitat</b>?", options: ["a. soil","b. moisture","c. predators","d. temperature"], answer: "c. predators" },
          { question: "3. 'The <b>rate of any biological process</b> is limited by that factor in <b>least amount relative</b> to requirement,so there is a single limiting factor.' This is the statement for", options: ["a. Liebig’s law of the minimum","b. Liebig’s law of the maximum","c. Shelford’s law of tolerance","d. Shelford’s law of intolerance"], answer: "a. Liebig’s law of the minimum" },
          { question: "4. <b>Transplantation experiments</b> are used to find", options: ["a. potential range","b. effective range","c. actual range","d. economic range"], answer: "a. potential range"},
          { question: "5. '<b>Quick movement over large distances</b>, often across unsuitable terrain' is a description of", options: ["a. diffusion","b. secular dispersal","c. jump dispersal","d. drifting"], answer: "c. jump dispersal" },
          { question: "6. <b>The movement of lions</b> across the Gir landscape is an example of", options: ["a. diffusion","b. secular dispersal","c. jump dispersal","d. drifting"], answer: "a. diffusion"},
          { question: "7. <b>Good climate</b> is a", options: ["a. chemical factor","b. demographic factor","c. push factor","d. pull factor"], answer: "d. pull factor"},
          { question: "8. <b>Scarcity of food</b> is a", options: ["a. chemical factor","b. demographic factor","c. push factor","d. pull factor"], answer: "c. push factor"},
          { question: "9. 'The <b>geographical distribution of a species</b> will be <b>controlled by</b> that environmental factor for which the organism has the <b>narrowest range of tolerance.</b>' This is the statement for", options: ["a. Liebig’s law of the minimum","b. Liebig’s law of the maximum","c. Shelford’s law of tolerance","d. Shelford’s law of intolerance"], answer: "c. Shelford’s law of tolerance"},
          { question: "10. The <b>movement of individuals</b> away <b>from their place of birth</b> or hatching or seed production into a new habitat or area <b>to survive and reproduce</b> is called", options: ["a. translocation","b. migration","c. dispersal","d. drifting"], answer: "c. dispersal"}
                  
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 8",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. According to Leopold, which of these is <b>not a tool of habitat management</b>?", options: ["a. fire","b. gun","c. cattle","d. sickle"], answer: "d. sickle" },
          { question: "2. Which of these correctly represents <b>the process of habitat fragmentation and loss</b>?", options: ["a. Original forest → Dissection → Perforation → Fragmentation → Attrition","b. Original forest → Dissection → Attrition → Fragmentation →Perforation","c. Original forest → Dissection → Perforation → Attrition →Fragmentation","d. Original forest → Dissection → Fragmentation → Perforation →Attrition"], answer: "a. Original forest → Dissection → Perforation → Fragmentation → Attrition" },
          { question: "3. We prefer those areas for the <b>creation of a conservation reserve</b> where <b>the level of threat</b> is", options: ["a. very high","b. medium","c. very low","d. non-existent"], answer: "b. medium" },
          { question: "4. The '<b>subset of physical and biotic environmental factors</b> that permit an <b>animal (or plant) to survive and reproduce</b>' is the definition of", options: ["a. habitat","b. ecosystem","c. biome","d. biosphere"], answer: "a. habitat"},
          { question: "5. <b>Captive breeding</b> is an example of", options: ["a. in-situ conservation","b. ex-situ conservation","c. in-situ preservation","d. ex-situ preservation"], answer: "b. ex-situ conservation" },
          { question: "6. Which of these <b>is a deterministic factor</b>?", options: ["a. environmental variation","b. forest fire","c. death rate","d. diseases"], answer: "c. death rate"},
          { question: "7. Which of these <b>is a stochastic factor</b>?", options: ["a. birth rate","b. death rate","c. population structure","d. environmental fluctuation"], answer: "d. environmental fluctuation"},
          { question: "8. <b>Zoo</b> is an example of", options: ["a. in-situ conservation","b. ex-situ conservation","c. in-situ preservation","d. ex-situ preservation"], answer: "b. ex-situ conservation"},
          { question: "9. The acronym <b>HIPPO does not include</b>", options: ["a. habitat loss","b. habitat enhancement","c. invasive species","d. human over-population"], answer: "b. habitat enhancement"},
          { question: "10. The acronym <b>HIPPO does not include</b>", options: ["a. habitat loss","b. invasive species","c. pollination","d. pollution"], answer: "c. pollination"}
                  
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 9",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. Which of these is a <b>positive check according to Malthus</b>?", options: ["a. late marriage","b. war","c. celibacy","d. moral restraint"], answer: "b. war" },
          { question: "2. The <b>demographic transition sees a society move</b> from", options: ["a. high birth rate, low death rate to low birth rate, low death rate","b. low birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate","c. high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate","d. high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, high death rate"], answer: "c. high birth rate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate" },
          { question: "3. According to <b>Malthusian model</b>,", options: ["a. Population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression","b. Population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in geometric progression","c. Population grows in arithmetic progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression","d. Population grows in arithmetic progression, food supply increases in geometric progression"], answer: "a. Population grows in geometric progression, food supply increases in arithmetic progression" },
          { question: "4. The book '<b>An Essay on the Principle of Population</b>' was written by", options: ["a. Darwin","b. Malthus","c. Spencer","d. Owens"], answer: "b. Malthus"},
          { question: "5. ___ is used to <b>identify</b> which <b>potential impacts are relevant to assess</b>. (Fill in the blank)", options: ["a. screening","b. scoping","c. reporting","d. review"], answer: "b. scoping" },
          { question: "6. Which of these is a <b>preventive check according to Malthus?</b>", options: ["a. foresight","b. vice","c. misery","d. flood"], answer: "a. foresight"},
          { question: "7. ___ determines which <b>projects or developments</b> require <b>a full or partial impact assessment study</b>.(Fill in the blank)", options: ["a. screening","b. scoping","c. reporting","d. review"], answer: "a. screening"},
          { question: "8. Which of these <b>is a pillar of sustainability</b>", options: ["a. social sustainability","b. industrial sustainability","c. agricultural sustainability","d. trans-boundary sustainability"], answer: "a. social sustainability"},
          { question: "9. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>pillar of sustainability</b>?", options: ["a. environmental sustainability","b. economic sustainability","c. trans-boundary sustainability","d. social sustainability"], answer: "c. trans-boundary sustainability"},
          { question: "10. The <b>quantum of human impacts</b> is given by", options: ["a. I = P × A × T","b. I = P + A + T","c. I = P + A - T","d. I = P - (A + T)"], answer: "a. I = P × A × T"}
                  
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 10",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>climatic forcing for Earth</b>?", options: ["a. changes in plate tectonics","b. changes in Earth's orbit","c. changes in Sun's orbit","d. changes in Sun's strength"], answer: "c. changes in Sun's orbit" },
          { question: "2. <b>Mesodebris</b> in the context of plastic debris has fragments of size", options: ["a. > 20 mm","b. 5 - 20 mm","c. < 5 mm","d. < 1 mm"], answer: "b. 5 - 20 mm" },
          { question: "3. <b>Macrodebris</b> in the context of plastic debris has fragments of size", options: ["a. > 20 mm","b. 5 - 20 mm","c. < 5 mm","d. < 1 mm"], answer: "a. > 20 mm" },
          { question: "4. '<b>Any changes in natural or human systems</b> that <b>inadvertently increase vulnerability to climatic stimuli</b>; an adaptation that does not succeed in reducing vulnerability but increases it instead' is a definition for", options: ["a. adaptation","b. mitigation","c. maladaptation","d. malmitigation"], answer: "c. maladaptation"},
          { question: "5. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>principle of ecological restoration<b>?", options: ["a. ecological integrity","b. long-term sustainability","c. benefits and engages scientists","d. informed by past and future"], answer: "c. benefits and engages scientists" },
          { question: "6. The government came up with a regulation that <b>incandescent bulbs be replaced by LED bulbs</b>, so that electricity consumption and release of carbon dioxide from power plants is reduced. In the context of climate change, such an action would be called", options: ["a. adaptation","b. mitigation","c. deceleration","d. maladaptation"], answer: "b. mitigation"},
          { question: "7. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>principle of ecological restoration</b>?", options: ["a. ecological integrity","b. short-term sustainability","c. benefits and engages society","d. informed by past and future"], answer: "b. short-term sustainability"},
          { question: "8. “The <b>ability of a system to adjust to climate change</b> (including climate variability and extremes) to moderate potential damages, to take advantage of opportunities, or to cope with the consequences” is a definition for", options: ["a. adaptive response","b. adaptive capacity","c. mitigative response","d. mitigative capacity"], answer: "b. adaptive capacity"},
          { question: "9. Which of these is <b>not</b> a <b>climatic forcing for Earth</b>?", options: ["a. changes in plate tectonics","b. changes in Earth's orbit","c. changes in Moon's orbit","d. changes in Sun's strength"], answer: "c. changes in Moon's orbit"},
          { question: "10. Because of climate change, <b>Mudumalai Tiger Reserve</b> is suffering from frequent droughts. The management has <b>built several artificial water holes</b> for animals, and fills them up regularly with tankers. In the context of climate change, such an action would be called", options: ["a. adaptation","b. mitigation","c. deceleration","d. maladaptation"], answer: "a. adaptation"}
                  
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 11",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. Which of these is correct?", options: ["a. R + G = M + F","b. R + M = G + F","c. R + F = M + G","d. R + G + M + F = 0"], answer: "a. R + G = M + F" },
          { question: "2. Which of these is <b>not</b> an <b>impact of toxic chemicals</b>?", options: ["a. lethal effects","b. sub-lethal effects","c. reduction of existing stressors","d. reduced fecundity"], answer: "c. reduction of existing stressors" },
          { question: "3. A <b>pest population</b> is called <b>controlled when</b>", options: ["a. it is not increasing","b. it is decreasing","c. it is not causing any economic damage","d. it is not causing excessive economic damage"], answer: "d. it is not causing excessive economic damage" },
          { question: "4. A <b>deciduous forest</b> in Madhya Pradesh was <b>converted to a mine</b>. <b>After</b> the mining operations were over, <b>the pits were filled up with soil</b> and species of deciduous forest <b>planted again</b>. This is an example of", options: ["a. recovery","b. restoration","c. enhancement","d. replacement"], answer: "b. restoration"},
          { question: "5. A <b>root zone treatment plant<b> is an example of", options: ["a. phytoremediation","b. biological control","c. biomagnification","d. bioaccumulation"], answer: "a. phytoremediation" },
          { question: "6. A <b>pest population</b> is called <b>uncontrolled</b> when", options: ["a. it is increasing","b. it is not decreasing","c. it is causing some economic damage","d. it is causing excessive economic damage"], answer: "d. it is causing excessive economic damage"},
          { question: "7. The <b>impact of El Nino</b> on <b>fishery collapse</b> in Peru is explained by", options: ["a. match hypothesis","b. mismatch hypothesis","c. match-mismatch hypothesis","d. none of these"], answer: "c. match-mismatch hypothesis"},
          { question: "8. Which of these is correct?", options: ["a. The maximum sustainable yield is near the beginning of the sigmoidal curve.","b. The maximum sustainable yield is near the mid-point of the sigmoidal curve.","c. The maximum sustainable yield is near the end of the sigmoidal curve.","d. None of these."], answer: "b. The maximum sustainable yield is near the mid-point of the sigmoidal curve."},
          { question: "9. <b>Ludwig's ratchet</b> predicts", options: ["a. decreasing harvesting rate","b. constant harvesting rate","c. increasing harvesting rate","d. fluctuating harvesting rate"], answer: "c. increasing harvesting rate"},
          { question: "10. A <b>deciduous forest</b> in Madhya Pradesh was <b>converted to a mine</b>. <b>After</b> the mining operations were over, the <b>pits were filled up with water</b> and a <b>lake was created</b>. It is now <b>visited by several migratory birds</b>. This is an example of", options: ["a. recovery","b. restoration","c. enhancement","d. replacement"], answer: "d. replacement"}
                  
        ]
      },

      {
        title: "Week 12",
        questions: [
          { question: "1. 'Enquiry into plants' is a book written by", options: ["a. Theophrastus","b. Linnaeus","c. Malthus","d. Humboldt"], answer: "a. Theophrastus" },
          { question: "2. The mitochondrion is a / an", options: ["a. Sub-cellular organelle","b. Cell","c. Tissue","d. Organ"], answer: "a. Sub-cellular organelle" },
          { question: "3. Which of these is not a pillar of sustainability?", options: ["a. environmental sustainability","b. economic sustainability","c. trans-boundary sustainability","d. social sustainability"], answer: "c. trans-boundary sustainability" },
          { question: "4. Good climate is a", options: ["a. chemical factor","b. demographic factor","c. push factor","d. pull factor"], answer: "d. pull factor"},
          { question: "5. Importance value varies from", options: ["a. 0 to 10","b. 0 to 50","c. 0 to 100","d. 0 to 300"], answer: "d. 0 to 300" },
          { question: "6. Consider the food chain: Grass → Grasshopper → Frog → Snake →Hawk. In this food chain,", options: ["a. frog is producer","b. frog is consumer and carnivore","c. frog is consumer and herbivore","d. frog is decomposer"], answer: "b. frog is consumer and carnivore"},
          { question: "7. The juvenile mortality rate is the annual number of deaths of juveniles per", options: ["a. 100 births","b. 1000 births","c. 100 live births","d. 1000 live births"], answer: "d. 1000 live births"},
          { question: "8. Because of climate change, Mudumalai Tiger Reserve is suffering from frequent droughts. The management has built several artificial water holes for animals, and fills them up regularly with tankers. In the context of climate change, such an action would be called", options: ["a. adaptation","b. mitigation","c. deceleration","d. maladaptation"], answer: "a. adaptation"},
          { question: "9. The scientific study of animal behaviour is called", options: ["a. behaviourism","b. ecology","c. ethology","d. prey-predator dynamics"], answer: "c. ethology"},
          { question: "10. Zoo is an example of", options: ["a. in-situ conservation","b. ex-situ conservation","c. in-situ preservation","d. ex-situ preservation"], answer: "b. ex-situ conservation"}
                  
        ]
      },

      


    // Add more weeks
  
  

    ]
